One way to learn the parameters
of the neural network,
so that it gives
you a good encoding
for your pictures of faces,
is to define and apply
gradient descent on the
triplet loss function.
Let's see what that means.
To apply the triplet loss you
need to compare pairs of images.
For example, given this picture,
to learn the parameters
of the neural network,
you have to look at several
pictures at the same time.
For example, given
this pair of images,
you want their encodings to be
similar because these
are the same person.
Whereas given this
pair of images,
you want their
encodings to be quite
different because these
are different persons.
In the terminology
of the triplet loss,
what you're going
to do is always
look at one anchor image,
and then you want
to distance between
the anchor and a positive image,
really a positive example,
meaning is the same
person, to be similar.
Whereas you want the anchor
when pairs are compared to have
a negative example for
their distances to be
much further apart.
This is what gives rise
to the term triplet loss,
which is that you
always be looking
at three images at a time.
You'll be looking
at an anchor image,
a positive image, as well
as a negative image.
I'm going to abbreviate
anchor, positive,
and negative as A, P,
and N. To formalize this,
what you want is for
the parameters of
your neural network
or for your encoding
to have the following property;
which is that you
want the encoding
between the anchor minus
the encoding of the
positive example,
you want this to be
small, and in particular,
less than or equal to
the distance or the squared norm
between the encoding of
the anchor and the
encoding of the negative,
whereof course this is d of A,
P and this is d of A,
N. You can think of d
as a distance function,
which is why we named it
with the alphabet d. Now,
if we move the term from
the right side of this
equation to the left side,
what you end up with is f of
A minus f of P squared minus,
I'm going to take the
right-hand side now,
minus f of N squared,
you want it to be less
than or equal to zero.
But now we're going to
make a slight change
to this expression, which is;
one trivial way to make
sure this is satisfied
is to just learn
everything equals zero.
If f always output zero,
then this is 0 minus
0, which is 0,
this is 0 minus 0, which
is 0, and so, well,
by saying f of any image
equals a vector of all zero's,
you can see almost trivially
satisfy this equation.
To make sure that
the neural network
doesn't just output zero,
for all the encodings,
or to make sure
that it doesn't set
all the encodings
equal to each other.
Another way for
the neural network
to give a trivial outputs is
if the encoding for
every image was
identical to the encoding
to every other image,
in which case you
again get 0 minus 0.
To prevent your neural
network from doing that,
what we're going to do is
modify this objective to say
that this doesn't need to be
just less than equal to zero,
it needs to be quite a
bit smaller than zero.
In particular, if we
say this needs to
be less than negative Alpha,
where Alpha is another
hyperparameter
then this prevents
a neural network
from outputting the
trivial solutions.
By convention, usually, we write
plus Alpha instead of
negative Alpha there.
This is also called a margin,
which is terminology that
you'd be familiar with
if you've also seen
the literature
on support vector machines,
but don't worry about
it if you haven't.
We can also modify
this equation on top
by adding this margin parameter.
Given example, let's say
the margin is set to 0.2.
If in this example d of
the anchor and the
positive is equal to 0.5,
then you won't be satisfied if
d between the anchor
and the negative,
was just a little bit
bigger, say 0.51.
Of one. Even though 0.51
is bigger than 0.5,
you're saying that's
not good enough.
We want d of A,N to be
much bigger than d of A,P.
In particular, you
want this to be
at least 0.7 or higher.
Alternatively,
to achieve this margin or
this gap of at least 0.2,
you could either push
this up or push this down
so that there is at
least this gap of
this hyperparameter
Alpha 0.2 between
the distance between
the anchor and the
positive versus the
anchor and the negative.
That's what having a margin
parameter here does.
Which is it pushes
the anchor-positive pair and
the anchor-negative pair
further away from each other.
Let's take this equation
we have here at
the bottom and on
the next slide,
formalize it and define
the triplet loss function.
The triplet loss function is
defined on triples of images.
Given three images: A,
P, and N, the anchor positive
and negative examples,
so the positive examples is of
the same person as the anchor,
but the negative is of
a different person
than the anchor.
We're going to define
the loss as follows.
The loss on this example,
which is really defined on
a triplet of images is,
let me first copy over what
we had on the previous slide.
That was f A minus f P squared
minus f A minus f N squared,
and then plus alpha,
the margin parameter.
What you want is for this to
be less than or equal to zero.
To define the loss function,
let's take the max
between this and zero.
The effect of taking
the max here is that
so long as this is
less than zero,
then the loss is zero
because the max is
something less than equal
to zero with zero is
going to be zero.
So long as you
achieve the goal of
making this thing I've
underlined in green,
so long as you've
achieved the objective of
making that less than
or equal to zero,
then the loss on this
example is equal to zero.
But if on the other hand,
if this is greater than zero,
then if you take the max,
the max will end up selecting
this thing I've underlined in
green and so you'd
have a positive loss.
By trying to minimize this,
this has the effect
of trying to send
this thing to be zero or
less than equal to zero.
Then so long as this zero
or less than equal to zero,
the neural network doesn't care
how much further negative it is.
This is how you
define the loss on
a single triplet and the
overall cost function for
your neural network can
be sum over a training set of
these individual losses
on different triplets.
If you have a
training set of say,
10,000 pictures with
1,000 different persons,
what you'd have to
do is take your
10,000 pictures and
use it to generate,
to select triplets like this,
and then train your
learning algorithm using
gradient descent on this
type of cost function,
which is really
defined on triplets
of images drawn from
your training set.
Notice that in order to define
this dataset of triplets,
you do need some
pairs of A and P,
pairs of pictures
of the same person.
For the purpose of
training your system,
you do need a dataset where you
have multiple pictures
of the same person.
That's why in this example
I said if you have
10,000 pictures of 1,000
different persons,
so maybe you have ten pictures,
on average of each of your
1,000 persons to make
up your entire dataset.
If you had just one
picture of each person,
then you can't actually
train this system.
But of course, after
having trained a system,
you can then apply it to
your one-shot learning problem
where for your face
recognition system,
maybe you have only
a single picture
of someone you might be
trying to recognize.
But for your training set,
you do need to
make sure you have
multiple images of
the same person,
at least for some people
in your training set,
so that you can have pairs of
anchor and positive images.
Now, how do you actually
choose these triplets to
form your training set?
One of the problems
is if you choose A,
P, and N randomly from
your training set,
subject to A and P being
the same person and A and
N being different persons,
one of the problems is that if
you choose them so
that they're random,
then this constraint is
very easy to satisfy.
Because given two randomly
chosen pictures of people,
chances are A and N are much
different than A and P.
I hope you still
recognize this notation.
Does d (A, P) will be high
written on the last few
slides of these encoding.
This is equal to
this squared norm
distance between
the encodings that we had
on the previous line.
But if A and N are two randomly
chosen different persons,
then there's a very
high chance that
this will be much bigger,
more than the margin helper,
than that term on the left and
the Neural Network won't
learn much from it.
To construct your training set,
what you want to do is
to choose triplets, A,
P, and N, they're the
''hard'' to train on.
In particular, what you
want is for all triplets
that this constraint
be satisfied.
A triplet that is
''hard'' would be if you
choose values for A, P,
and N so that may be d (A,
P) is actually quite
close to d (A, N).
In that case, the
learning algorithm has
to try extra hard to take
this thing on the right
and try to push it up or take
this thing on the left
and try to push it down
so that there is at
least a margin of
alpha between the left
side and the right side.
The effect of choosing
these triplets is that it
increases the
computational efficiency
of your learning algorithm.
If you choose the
triplets randomly,
then too many triplets would be
really easy and gradient descent
won't do anything because
you're Neural Network would
get them right pretty
much all the time.
It's only by choosing
''hard'' to triplets
that the gradient
descent procedure
has to do some work
to try to push
these quantities further
away from those quantities.
If you're interested,
the details are
presented in this paper
by Florian Schroff,
Dmitry Kalenichenko,
and James Philbin,
where they have a
system called FaceNet,
which is where a lot
of the ideas I'm
presenting in this
video had come from.
By the way, this is
also a fun fact about
how algorithms are often
named in the Deep
Learning World,
which is if you work
in a certain domain,
then we call that Blank.
You often have a system called
Blank Net or Deep Blank.
We've been talking
about Face recognition.
This paper is called FaceNet,
and in the last video,
you just saw Deep Face.
But this idea of Blank
Net or Deep Blank is
a very popular way of
naming algorithms in the
Deep Learning World.
You should feel free
to take a look at
that paper if you
want to learn some of
these other details
for speeding up
your algorithm by choosing
the most useful
triplets to train on;
it is a nice paper.
Just to wrap up, to
train on triplet loss,
you need to take
your training set
and map it to a lot of triples.
Here is a triple with an
Anchor and a Positive,
both of the same person and
a Negative of a
different person.
Here's another one where
the Anchor and Positive
are of the same person,
but the Anchor and Negative are
of different persons and so on.
What you do, having to find
this training set of
Anchor, Positive,
and Negative triples is use
gradient descent to try to
minimize the cost function
J we defined on
an earlier slide.
That will have the effect of
backpropagating to
all the parameters
of the Neural Network in
order to learn an
encoding so that
d of two images
will be small when
these two images are of the
same person and they'll
be large when these are two
images of different persons.
That's it for the triplet loss
and how you can use it to train
a Neural Network to output
a good encoding for
face recognition.
Now, it turns out that today's
Face recognition systems,
especially the large-scale
commercial face
recognition systems
are trained on very
large datasets.
Datasets north of a million
images are not uncommon.
Some companies are
using north of
10 million images
and some companies
have north of a100
million images
with which they try to
train these systems.
These are very large datasets,
even by modern standards,
these dataset assets are
not easy to acquire.
Fortunately, some of these
companies have trained
these large networks and
posted parameters online.
Rather than trying to train one
of these networks from scratch,
this is one domain
where because of
the sheer data volumes sizes,
it might be useful
for you to download
someone else's pre-trained model
rather than do everything
from scratch yourself.
But even if you do download
someone else's
pre-trained model,
I think it's still
useful to know
how these algorithms
were trained in
case you need to apply
these ideas from
scratch yourself for
some application.
That's it for the triplet loss.
In the next video, I
want to show you also
some other variations on
Siamese networks and how
to train these systems.
Let's go on to the next video.